<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Benjamin Laken</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://benlaken.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://benlaken.com/</id><updated>2017-01-26T11:09:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>First days as a Data Scientist at Vizzuality</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/Vizzuality_post1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-26T11:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-26T11:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2017-01-26:Vizzuality_post1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/madrid_banner.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having spent the last 10 years in Universities and Research Institutes,
I had seen many colleagues and friends make the shift from the
public to the private-sector, particularly into Data Science roles. I was unsure what life would be
like after making the change myself. I am now two weeks in to my transition to
life as a Data Scientist at &lt;a href="http://www.vizzuality.com"&gt;Vizzuality&lt;/a&gt;, and so far it has been quite exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many interesting projects being developed here that feed directly
to policy-makers and influence public-opinion. Projects like the &lt;a href="http://www.vizzuality.com/projects/global-forest-watch"&gt;Global Forest Watch&lt;/a&gt;. And in some ways that feels a lot
like the day-to-day life in a high-quality university group, where people work on projects
or synthesis reports which reach the desks of critical people. Except, whereas
universities felt bureaucratic and institutional, Vizzuality feels dynamic and modern: It
works at a totally different pace, and generally aims at a far larger and more impactful
audience. Of course there is also the dimension of a profit motive behind the
private-sector, but it seems that at Vizzuality, the ethos is to actively push
towards projects and services that raise awareness,
and encourage responsible stewardship of our ecosystem at a planetary-scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for me, my past year as a &lt;a href="http://www.rse.ac.uk/who.html"&gt;Research Software Engineer&lt;/a&gt; at University College London
prepared me for the day-to-day tasks which I am currently working on:
As more time goes on, it's clearer-and-clearer that the &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-it-services/research-software-development"&gt;group&lt;/a&gt; that UCL
(and &lt;a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=JHETH53"&gt;Dr. James Heatherington&lt;/a&gt; in particular) created is the future-face of
Research in the University setting: the abstraction of the skills required to perform a
research project from the domain specific knowledge; creating effective teams
of dynamic computer-science literate people, who understand the scientific method,
and the way knowledge is created. It was, in fact, the creation of a Data Science group,
focused on research and reproducibility!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, coming from this group, I felt pretty happy to hit the ground running at Vizzuality, and in the past two
weeks at Vizzuality, I have had a chance to help them develop a new Open Source Python library called &lt;a href="https://github.com/Vizzuality/sql2gee"&gt;sql2gee&lt;/a&gt;, which converts
SQL requests into calls to &lt;a href="https://earthengine.google.com"&gt;Google's Earth Engine&lt;/a&gt;, and should let us easily use the
data on that platform in future Vizzuality products. So this has been very positive
for me so far, as I happen to love the Earth Engine, Open Source, and Python, not
to mention the prospect of contributing to projects that could contribute to creating a
more sustainable future. Exactly why I, and many others, became scientists in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Open Source"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Data Science"></category></entry><entry><title>Pelican + Github = A better way to website!</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/New_static_site.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-02T15:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-02T15:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2017-01-02:New_static_site.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/pelican_banner.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the astute recurring visitor may have noticed, I have a new site! I have been told that it doesn't look as impressive as my old one just yet. But I assure you that the new site is certainly forward progress, as it will be much easier for me to maintain and develop in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since around 2010, I hosted my website with Dreamhost, and made it using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Django_(web_framework)"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; and SQL.
While it was fun to have a reason to play with those tools, it was definitely overkill for my needs, and publishing new content was harder than it needed to be. Not to mention I never quite managed to find time to debug the site fully, or keep it's code it up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, those days are now over thanks to Github, &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://travis-ci.org"&gt;Travis&lt;/a&gt;! My new site is static, generated using Pelican, with &lt;a href="http://jinja.pocoo.org"&gt;Jninja2&lt;/a&gt; templates. The posts are all written in markdown, and creating new content is now as easy as typing out a quick plain-text doc, pushing it to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/blogsite"&gt;blogs Github repo&lt;/a&gt;, and then letting Travis do the work of automatically pulling the repo, building the site, and pushing the actual web pages to gh-pages branch on Github, where they are served with my old top-level domain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this means the site is much simpler, cheaper, and more lightweight, and, more importantly, I should be able to focus much more on content. Horray!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see a guide of how to do this for yourself, I found a few, such as &lt;a href="https://marpat.github.io/python-anaconda-and-pelican-on-windows.html"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. You can also grab a copy of my repo, and play with it. Feel free to use the template, a forked version of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/pure"&gt;Pure theme&lt;/a&gt; and adapted. If you are looking for an even easier solution you can also do the same thing using the &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/github-pages/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, but personally I wanted a Python-based solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One complication of this set up is that you have to give Travis an ssh key to push to your repo, so this requires you to set up Travis deploy key, but it is straightforward (&lt;a href="https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/private-dependencies/"&gt;details here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice feature has been Pelican's plugins, which are easy to use. I simply added the plugin repo as a submodule to my blogsite, then declare which one I want to use in the settings file, and
viola: simple YouTube embedding, Tag-clouds, footnotes, formatted code with syntax highlighting, and loads of other nice features to play with!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>How can I begin to improve my workflow?</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/how_to_begin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-01T09:49:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-01T09:49:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-10-01:how_to_begin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/journey_banner.jpg" title="Original image by Hanna Norlin" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A familiar situation?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you are toiling away at your project with nothing but your wits, a few hand-me-down scripts, and a supervisor who only has time to interact with you as they hurriedly walk down the corridor on their way to their next meeting? Perhaps it seems like it will be much easier to just get to work hammering away at your task, the way you were originally shown?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you saw a talk or read an article about the world of Open Science, and you are starting to have a strong suspicion that there must be a better way to work than the approach you have been using up-till-now: one that may even give you skills that people in the land that lays beyond academia will find attractive! You have heard about tools like Python, version control, and this vague idea of Open Science. But in practical terms, how can you begin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have a project with a file structure that looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;└── my_project
    │
    ├── Code
    │   ├── process_raw_data.f77  &amp;lt;--- Heart of the project, written in 90&amp;#39;s by, uh, someone...
    │   └── calculate_result.mat  &amp;lt;--- The postdoc who wrote this already left to work for a bank...
    │
    ├── Data
    │   ├── raw_experiment1.txt  &amp;lt;--- This is the raw data from my instrument
    │   ├── raw_experiment2.txt
    │   ├── raw_experiment3.txt
    │   └── processed_data.dat  &amp;lt;--- Postdoc&amp;#39;s code makes this, which I can put into Excel!
    │
    ├── output1.txt             &amp;lt;--- The postdocs code made this, which I can put into excel to examine...
    ├── experiment1.xlsx        &amp;lt;--- Finally, I can do something useful with this $*#@!
    ├── experiment2.xlsx
    ├── my_report_v3.docx       &amp;lt;--- The start of my thesis, or new paper
    └── summary_results.xlsx    &amp;lt;--- Summary excel sheet, so I can clean up my final results
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this folder, there is an old FORTRAN program (&lt;code&gt;Code/process_raw_data.f77&lt;/code&gt;) that you got from your supervisor, it was written several decades ago and there is no one around who you can ask about this code. (Maybe there is no one even left alive who worked on it...) To get results you start by editing that file: maybe all you really need to do is change one line to point the code at some raw data you got from an instrument (e.g. &lt;code&gt;Data/raw_experiment1.txt&lt;/code&gt;) and compile/run the program. On your first day your supervisor told you the exact commands to type to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old program might create an intermediate file, something like &lt;code&gt;Data/processed_data.dat&lt;/code&gt;. That file is a mess, way to complicated to deal with (Big Endian? Binary what? carriage control characters?). Luckily a postdoc who used to be in your group left behind a Matlab script to process that data into something you can read into Excel. So you run &lt;code&gt;Code/calculate_result.mat&lt;/code&gt;, and get &lt;code&gt;output.txt&lt;/code&gt;, after some cut-and-paste skills you then have your comprehensible data in a spreadsheet and can begin the real task of analysing it, which was the reason you are doing your work in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You make some analysis, spread across multiple pages of your Excel workbook, and end up producing some figures and tables which you put into your word document, write your text, send to your supervisor, await comments and pray they don't ask for any changes that would send you back to square 1!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most common workflow you will find at Universities and companies the world over. Working in this way is really labour intensive, and also incredibly irreproducible, &lt;a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/science/a22577/genetics-papers-excel-errors/"&gt;error-prone&lt;/a&gt;! (The &lt;a href="http://modeling-languages.com/whats-bus-factor-software-project/"&gt;bus-factor&lt;/a&gt; of projects like these are usually very low.) It would be almost impossible for you to ensure someone could recreate the results presented in your final document without you sat beside them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;You can download our code from the URL supplied. Good luck downloading the only postdoc who can get it to run, though &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/overlyhonestmethods?src=hash"&gt;#overlyhonestmethods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ian Holmes (@ianholmes) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ianholmes/status/288689712636493824"&gt;January 8, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is there is no where to go but up, and any change to this workflow would be a positive one! If you need to produce results quickly, then it likely isn't feasible to just learn some new tools, snap-your fingers, and immediately change this workflow. Instead, you will have to gradually migrate towards a fully Open Science approach, perhaps over the course of several projects (like I did).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Starting the journey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best place to start is to download &lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/downloads"&gt;Anaconda Python&lt;/a&gt; from Continuum Analytics, you don't need administrator privileges, and it works on Windows, Mac, and Nix* systems. Get one with Python version 3, not 2. (If you need to switch later on that will be easy, but by default you should try to work in Python 3.) Also download &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href="https://git-for-windows.github.io"&gt;Git-Bash&lt;/a&gt; if you are on windows).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that trifecta of the shell, a high-level programming language and a version control system you are ready to begin! The next step is to run through a couple of tutorials. If you cant get yourself to a &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry course&lt;/a&gt;, you can run through their materials on their website. Also have a look at &lt;a href="https://www.codecademy.com/learn/all"&gt;CodeAcademy&lt;/a&gt; (particularly their &lt;em&gt;'Command Line'&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;'Learn Git'&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;'Learn Python'&lt;/em&gt; lessons). You will probably pick up the basics of Python and Bash in just a few days sufficiently to begin using these tools for your own work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Project triage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Step 1: Moving from Excel to a few bad bits of code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest place to start improving your workflow is on the part that is most labour-intensive and least reproducible: usually this means the Excel workbooks. Instead of reading the data into Excel, read it with Python, and try to create some scripts that can do your analysis tasks. I realise this sounds like me explaining how to play the piano by saying &lt;em&gt;"Step 1: sit in front of a piano. Step 2: play the piano"&lt;/em&gt;, and perhaps at first you will struggle a little to do tasks which you know you could do in a couple of clicks in Excel. However, after following a few online tutorials you will see that you can copy and paste large portions of code from tutorials with small changes that will let you read data from a file, do many cool operations (using tools like &lt;a href="http://pandas.pydata.org"&gt;Pandas&lt;/a&gt; for example), and then plot (e.g. using &lt;a href="http://matplotlib.org"&gt;Matplotlib&lt;/a&gt;). Even if your code is awful at least it is automated, and can be tracked with version control tools and improved later. Maybe you will even keep a few Excel files while you are still going through a transition, and that is totally fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Step 2: Minor improvements = big time-saving&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's assume you've started adding a few simple Python scripts to your project that just look like a long list of &lt;em&gt;"Read this data, do X and Y then make a plot"&lt;/em&gt;. And maybe you're starting to see a few small benefits, like saving time when you have to re-run your workflow to add more data or tweak something small. But on the whole, you might feel like this hasn't really saved you much time yet. You may even feel like you've lost time learning Python, and have gotten quite frustrated a few times along the way wrapping your mind around new ways of thinking about your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't despair! Imagine you are going to start a new project, and you start to notice that there are a few similarities with your old one. You get the feeling you can start to re-use bits of your old python code again, maybe even improve them a little. Now you will start to see one of the powerful benefits of working like this: &lt;strong&gt;abstraction&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the sake of explanation, imagine your task is multiplying two numbers together thousands of times. The first time you solved this problem, you only knew enough Python to write it out like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;result_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;result_2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;result_3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value_6&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;etc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now you have been working with Python for a little while, you realise you can make an abstract solution, that will solve this problem once-and-for-all, a solution you can re-use. It might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much simpler! and when you call your inputs in a loop and feed them into this function it seems to works brilliantly! But actually, it is a little fragile like this. As you learn more, you will find that if you add a few more pieces to the code, you can get really important benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pytest&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input_2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;ValueError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Error: inputs are not numbers&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;test_my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;3.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;5.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;19.25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pytest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;raises&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ne"&gt;ValueError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;my_tool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;NA&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is really remarkable what's going on in these few lines of code: Your tool starts by checking that it has been given the right type of data (numerical data), by seeing if it can convert it to an integer.  If the inputs are good, it will do your task. If it can't, the program will stop, giving an Error: so you wont accidentally process bad values and wind up with junk values in your results that you have to hunt down later!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things get more interesting when we see what comes next - a test! This is a reality check, to make sure that no matter how you extend or change your tool in the future, it will always produce results that make sense. It even checks that the tool fails when it should, so you know that despite changes you may make tomorrow, it wont start giving back unexpected results, adding errors into your results. This is really important, as projects change over time, and it is guaranteed you won't write a perfect program first time. So when you go back in the future and change your functions, you can be relatively confident you wont inadvertently introduce errors into your work. You can run this test with &lt;a href="http://docs.pytest.org/en/latest/"&gt;pytest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to over-state the time-saving and productivity boosting potential of making small, easy-to-understand solutions, that are re-useable, and include tests: your final workflow should be a daisy-chain of tools like this. If you can get this far into updating your working approach, you will be making great progress, and will be poised to take advantage of some really amazing tools in the future, and share with &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk"&gt;communities of people&lt;/a&gt; already using them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post was part 2 in a series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banner image by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hanorlin/"&gt;Hanna Norlin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Reproducibility"></category><category term="Open Science"></category><category term="Software"></category></entry><entry><title>Trust me, I'm a doctor</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/Trust_me.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-30T14:23:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-30T14:23:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-09-30:Trust_me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="./images/lego_banner.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may surprise a few people to learn that this cliché is more-or-less accurate when it comes to most modern research. More-often-than-not researchers expect us to take their results on faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workflows that researchers use to produce results are now, almost without exception, based on extremely complex software -- more complex than even than the researchers themselves usually appreciate! They typically involve multiple stages of data processing, perhaps spread across several people and several computer systems, with analysis scripts written in various languages, intermediate stages of manual file manipulations, maybe even the odd spreadsheet program. The core of an analysis may often be written in a rush to meet one deadline or another. And this is usually done without documentation, tests, or version control, to ultimately produce a figure or value that makes up 'a result'. The net effect of this creates a situation ominously named the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis"&gt;replication crisis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An experienced software developer friend-of-mine once remarked, when looking at a typical example of a modern research pipeline&lt;sup id=sf-Trust_me-1-back&gt;&lt;a href=#sf-Trust_me-1 class=simple-footnote title=" A pipeline is a colloquial way of referring to all parts of the process of turning raw data into a final analysis"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, that 'it was no better than a random number generator'. The pipeline was undoubtedly of significant importance to the group that made it. But he knew that no matter if you are an unpaid PhD student, or a highly-paid developer working for Google, code has bugs. Many bugs. They are hard enough to find when you use good software development practices, but an opaque research pipeline makes debugging virtually impossible. It is pure arrogance to think that as a researcher you have perfectly functional software on what is essentially a first release, and people should just be satisfied to accept your results at face value!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most mainstream, respectable journals now support Open Access and also highlight a commitment to reproducibility to some degree, usually by advising the authors to place their data or code in accessible databases or supplying them as supplementary materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, reviewers almost never attempt to verify that they can reproduce an authors result, or examine whether the steps they have taken in their analysis pipeline are flawed in some way that might compromise the papers conclusions. In fact, as a reviewer, requesting data or code in order to check the work you have been given to check is usually met with quizzical and uncertain replies -- as if neither the editors or authors know what to do next!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, authors want to avoid giving code out at all costs: they tend to view such requests as an unreasonable level of scrutiny, or even a loss of intellectual property. They are also well-aware that if people care to look in detail they are likely to find the metaphorical duct-tape holding their research together. (Duct-tape, which they rationalise, they will address in the next iteration of their work.) If a reviewer does ask to see code, usually what happens next is that they are treated like a biased or unreasonable reviewer, and the authors may try to encourage the editors to favour the opinions of the other reviewers who didn't rock the boat. Even if journals state in their publication policies sentiments that 'data and code used to produce results must be made available with publication of the manuscripts', this is rarely enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, readers are usually left to fend for themselves when it comes to piecing together what authors have actually done (which may be all-but un-intuitable based on the text of a paper). The only ways skeptical readers can decide whether or not to put stock in what they are reading is usually by a mix of a papers logical consistency (&lt;a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/doing-good-science/evaluating-scientific-claims-or-do-we-have-to-take-the-scientists-word-for-it/"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;), agreement to meta-studies, or the reputation of the authors or institutes to which they are associated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/raymondh"&gt;Raymond Hettinger&lt;/a&gt; says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"There has to be a better way!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As analysis pipelines have become increasingly complex, simply saying X result was produced with Y is not useful. It is well understood that more information is needed, such as metadata about the researchers systems, library versions, automated workflows or makefiles. Many professions, including software developers, have reached the understanding that reproducing peoples results is a difficult problem. (Hence the enormous popularity of systems such as Docker and Vagrant.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A difficult reality is that while most researchers are able to cobble together steps to go from raw data to a result, they are not able to do so in anything close to a reproducible manner -- this is important if they want to use their analysis as evidence to affect society! There are two options to address this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Improve the training and awareness of researchers, and enforce practices that allow for reproducibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now many resources encouraging researchers to &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/2010/101013/full/467753a.html"&gt;publish their code&lt;/a&gt; or showing them how to adopt &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/interactive-notebooks-sharing-the-code-1.16261"&gt;better tools for reproducibility&lt;/a&gt;. Training is being encouraged by non-profit groups such as &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;, driving increased awareness is spreading across disciplines. However, it is not spreading evenly, leading almost to a two-tier system of 1) researchers who are updating their methods and attempting to work with best practices, vs. 2) old-school researchers, who stalwartly stick to old methods, and in turn pass those practices to their students (see my last blog post for more on this). Hopefully at some point a critical mass will be achieved, and the minority of hold-outs who refuse to support the reproducibility of their work will be ostracised. (Happy thoughts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Create a specialist position, such as &lt;a href="http://www.rse.ac.uk/who.html"&gt;Research Software Engineers&lt;/a&gt;, and organisations such as the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk"&gt;Software Sustainability Institute&lt;/a&gt;,  whose purpose  &lt;br&gt;
is to work with researchers, bringing their expertise in creating research software to domain specific problems as needed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this, universities must essentially create a new class of position; one enticing enough to attract and retain talented people that understand both how research works, and also have a good grasp of software development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we are in a state where you have no good option to determine the reliability of published results, short of spending an inordinate amount of time as a scientific Sherlock Holmes; painstakingly piecing together an analysis from a few public datasets and some lonely clues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banner image credit &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/spacebarpark/"&gt;Kevin spacebarpark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class=simple-footnotes&gt;&lt;li id=sf-Trust_me-1&gt; A pipeline is a colloquial way of referring to all parts of the process of
turning raw data into a final analysis &lt;a href=#sf-Trust_me-1-back class=simple-footnote-back&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="Reproducibility"></category><category term="Journals"></category><category term="Research"></category><category term="Software"></category></entry><entry><title>Academic archetypes: an anti-pattern for reproducibility</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/academic_archetypes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-06T10:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-06T10:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-09-06:academic_archetypes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/tale_of_three.png" title="Original image by Jorge Chan" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meet the academics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raoul is a diligent and hard working PhD student: He immerses himself in his subject, and feels like there is so much to learn with so little time. He may often feel on the outside looking in, racked with doubt, wondering whether he could ever contribute something meaningful to their field. His supervisor has given him some old code, allegedly related to an unrecognisably early version of their PhD project, maybe in something like FORTRAN or Matlab. Peter doesn't have time to stop and smell the roses, he has to get cracking to produce results, write papers, defend, and get on the fast-track to academic success! For him, his main priority is learning his subject, and generating a new contribution to his field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasha has put in the endless hours grinding, made it through the trauma of her PhD with only minor mental scarring, and found that she now has more work and responsibilities than ever, but with even less time! She needs to get uber serious, as she tries to publish papers from her thesis, go to conferences, and produce 'trend-setting' new research to become known in her field and make it out of 'permadoc hell'. She might have a steadily growing collection of hacky scripts to process their data, or maybe even some monolithic Excel spreadsheets with VBA macros. She couldn't possibly change the way she works now: it would be a huge set-back not only to loose all that past work, but also to invest all the time learning new tools. And hey, what she has been doing has worked up till now---no journal has ever even asked about her code---so it would be foolish to waste the time changing now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assistant Professor Smith has worked hard and made many sacrifices to get where she is, yet she is going to have to push even harder to reach tenure. Time for her to rise to prominence in her field and earn international renown. She will likely travel several times each month, and compete in an ever more cut-throat environment for funding, whilst simultaneously building a dynamic research group populated with people like Postdoc Tasha and PhD Student Raoul. All to prove to her university that she has what it takes to be a permanent staff member! Not only would Assistant Professor Smith never dream of going back to square 1 and learning basic working methods again, but in reality she probably rarely does any research herself any more. Instead, she directs her underlings when she has time, and encourages them to re-use and build on whatever pipelines and scripts she built-up on her climb to her current post, as that has the least mental overhead for her to lend a hand when her minions get into trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's the problem?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If successful, Assistant Professor Smith will join the ranks of tenured professors in her University and take on more teaching and administration responsibilities. Over time, her practices may be enshrined in courseware and become part of the institutional practices at their University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of enabling best research practices to spread, these profiles have an anti-pattern built into them. Bad practices are left uncorrected as there is no incentive to improve and refine old work, optimise working methods for reproducibility. In fact, stopping to improve existing research could be a serious competitive disadvantage: You have to remember that at each stage up this career pyramid there are far-fewer positions, and the competition and stakes becomes far greater. By the time Assistant Professor Smith goes after their tenure, they have almost certainly invested 100% of their adult life into getting their position, professionally and personally. To let up for even a moment could be the difference between being the best, and being the second best candidate --- a disaster, as their peers are all seeking the same goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So academics become trapped in an endless race against the clock and their peers to produce new results and gain all the kudos possible. As a result, many research pipe-lines simply remain black-boxes, perhaps no better than random-number generators. Many researchers have no immediate way to reliably check their various scripts and disjointed tools are not producing incorrect results, and are not aware of how to go about doing so even if they wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the lifetime of academic software, the key component driving modern science, is usually strongly correlated to the length of the authors contracts. Usually a researchers main concern revolves around getting code working on their local machine, and producing results one time, often with multiple (undocumented) intermediate processing steps. Thus, there is a strong tendency for projects to generate abandonware: unmaintained software which rapidly degrades into obsolescence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can Student Raoul, in the course of their arduous career journey to the level of Professor Smith, hope to break this anti-pattern? When should they start? And what might the impacts of doing so be to their career? Should they even bother? Over the course of the next few blog-posts I hope to address this question and more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original banner image by &lt;a href="http://www.phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=1537"&gt;Jorge Chan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Reproducibility"></category><category term="Software"></category><category term="Science"></category></entry><entry><title>Testing, testing</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/testing_code.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-17T09:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-06-17T09:27:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-06-17:testing_code.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/code_banner.jpg" title="Original image by James Clarke" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regression testing, unit tests, Test driven development, automated
testing, defensive programming. Despite years in research, these were
not terms I had heard, not from my supervisors or peers, nor at
conferences, and certainly not in journals or other scientific forums.
Yet after working for a few months in &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-it-services"&gt;UCL's
RITS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-it-services/about/research-software-development"&gt;Research Software
Development
team&lt;/a&gt;,
a group that emphasises software development to improve Science, I have
woken up to the reality that software developers have known for a long
time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Code without tests is broken by design"&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;a href="https://jacobian.org"&gt;Jacob
Kaplan-Moss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that all the scientific code written by myself and the
hundreds of thousands of other researchers globally that more-or-less
ignores testing is useless? Not at all. It does means that the code
might not be robust, may be unable to deal with edge cases, and may
(probably) hide bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have ever tried to re-use a script written to produce data for a
specific publication, you will already know that it can take some work
to get it to run in a different environment or on different data. But
without tests there is know way to even know if the code works the way
in which the original authors intended it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone interested in getting started with testing (it's never too
late), check out the course material from UCL's &lt;a href="http://development.rc.ucl.ac.uk/training/engineering/"&gt;MPHYG001: Research
software Engineering with
Python&lt;/a&gt;, by the
RSD team leader &lt;a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=JHETH53"&gt;Dr. James
Heatherington&lt;/a&gt;.
There is also nice material from the &lt;a href="http://pythontesting.net/test-podcast/"&gt;Test and Code
podcast&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brianokken"&gt;Brian
Okken&lt;/a&gt;, including a useful ebook. He can
also be heard discussing testing on the excellent &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/talkpython"&gt;Talk Python to
Me&lt;/a&gt; podcast &lt;a href="https://talkpython.fm/episodes/show/45/the-python-testing-column-now-a-thing"&gt;Episode
#45&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my quick education in testing I would say that intentionally
writing code without tests is equivalent actively trying to ignore
problems. In a purely software development context this would simply be
passing on a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_debt"&gt;technical
debt&lt;/a&gt;. In the context of
Science however, the negative impacts will land on you much more
directly. As it's your personal reputation that rests on the credibility
of your work. So start testing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banner photo credit &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jc/2824253273/in/photolist-4FGR4v-5iz36X-8G1uXV-7w2Qiv-o5zxto-9AwFd3-3cpzbd-9AtL4n-48zoQq-9AwFjj-D3Ggt-DmzuR-pSfzW-xwTA7-7vnuo-pScys-zPTaq-7qd5hz-r7MxJ-qMjh4-a4wyn-r7MxK-zPRkT-pScyx-pScyw-unfhM-pScyu-pScyv-pScyt"&gt;James
Clarke&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Testing"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Software"></category></entry><entry><title>A Research Software Developer in London</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/RDS_london.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-10T09:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-06-10T09:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-06-10:RDS_london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been a while since my last post, and a lot has changed. My time at the Department of Geosciences in the University of Oslo as a postdoc research fellow sadly came to a close; it was hard to move on and leave behind my friends and Norwegian life. I have many great memories of Norway, and hope it won't be too long before I return. Perhaps that will even be my last postdoc and the end of my professionally active research career. After 3 postdoc contracts I would say that is a bitter-sweet thought, as there are many pros and many cons of being a postdoc-probably a mix which you won't find in any other job-but 6 years of that lifestyle may be my limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last February I moved to a new type of job, a Research Software Developer. I am now part of a small team at the University College of London, which itself is part of the &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-it-services"&gt;Research IT services department&lt;/a&gt;. There are around eight of us working together supporting various projects from departments across the university, and we are linked to the UK's &lt;a href="http://www.software.ac.uk"&gt;Software Sustainability Institute&lt;/a&gt;. The team are the smiling people pictured! The goal of the team is essentially to use modern software development practices to improve research and researchers, making projects more reliable, usable, correct, and functional beyond the funding period of specific projects, and training researchers in tools and practices that support productivity and reproducibility. We are fostering Open Science practices: something that I find very motivating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/ucl_team.jpg" title="UCL RSD team summer 2016" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also run Software Carpentry workshops: the next one is &lt;a href="http://ucl-rits.github.io/2016-06-22-UCL_software_carpentry/"&gt;coming up soon&lt;/a&gt;. It will be my first since I officially became an instructor, and the first which I will co-lead, so I am very excited about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new job is a big change of pace for me, each day is invariably a significant learning experience. So far I have gotten-to-grips with lots of new tools and computer science methods. I have learnt a lot about programming practices, code testing and various packages, version control, and lately I have been familiarising myself with virtual machines using &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.vagrantup.com"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fun never stops: over the next few months there are lots more big changes to come, including another move - this time to Madrid, my wife's home city. One of the big benefits of moving away from active research is that it has freed me up to focus on other (albeit closely related) interests. My main one being improving science in general through spreading Open Science practices. I hope to have some news about an exciting new project I am starting relating to this soon. I also hope to find the time to improve my website soon, and perhaps post some more blogs and code examples from my three 2016 publications. I am also hoping to indirectly continue my past research by supporting my old collaborators-particularly with the new development methods I am learning-so hopefully there will be more updates on that too in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Software"></category><category term="Research"></category><category term="UCL"></category></entry><entry><title>Old Science invigorated with Open Science</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/paper_update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-24T13:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-03-24T13:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-03-24:paper_update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/banner_old_sci.png" title="Original image by James Clarke" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last November someone e-mailed me a strange request, they wanted to use
a method from &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/full_html/2013/01/swsc130020/swsc130020.html"&gt;a paper I wrote in
2013&lt;/a&gt;.
Shocking I know. I had included in the paper a link to some IDL code
meant to reproduce the figures, of course, it was already broken. It had
aged badly, inaccessible a full 2 years ahead of &lt;a href="http://www.clir.org/pubs/archives/ensuring.pdf"&gt;Jeff Rotheberg's
prediction&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;"digital
information lasts forever — or five years, whichever comes first"&lt;/em&gt;).
After digging through my file system and recovering the old script I had
the feeling that if the link not been broken it would probably not have
been of much help. Needless to say, at the time I wrote the paper I
thought the approach I took was great. I didn't know much about coding
then, and I hadn't heard of version control either. Although, to be
fair, no one in the field I was working in talked about these issues or
showed much interest in code. In fact, asking to see peoples code was a
good way to loose friends (&lt;em&gt;"You don't trust me?"&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;"You want to
steal my work?"&lt;/em&gt;). A few years on, and I now know enough to see that
approach I took was not terribly helpful if the aim was to create
reproducible science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driven by examples from a new generation of researchers who break from
the &lt;em&gt;"publish or perish"&lt;/em&gt; model and instead operate under the &lt;em&gt;"share
and thrive"&lt;/em&gt; philosophy (people like &lt;a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus
Brown&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.jesshamrick.com/blog/"&gt;Jessica
Hamrick&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://wesmckinney.com"&gt;Wes
Mckninney&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://pyaos.johnny-lin.com"&gt;Johnny Wei-Bing
Lin&lt;/a&gt;), I have invested time into learning
the tools and practices of the Open Science community. Since a lot of
effort went into writing my 2013 paper, and I sincerely wanted people in
my field to adopt the methods it discusses, I committed to the challenge
of re-writing the code, and thinking how to communicate the ideas more
effectively. I decided to mix the (peer-reviewed) original article text,
with re-written Python code and new figures (I had seen such an approach
used before, in a &lt;a href="http://camdavidsonpilon.github.io/Probabilistic-Programming-and-Bayesian-Methods-for-Hackers/"&gt;Bayesian text book written in the
Notebook&lt;/a&gt;,
which I recommend you have a look at), so I diligently set about trying
to recreate my own work from days past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As any researcher will tell you, this is a dangerous game, analogous to
the moment just before someone accidentally shoots themselves whilst
cleaning their own gun. This is because scientists are now essentially
programmers, programmers without a background in computer science,
usually without training or assistance of any kind in fact, who
generally don't have code-reviews, write tests, share their code, or
sometimes even understand the nuances of the language they are working
in. (For some discussion on this see the PLOS article &lt;a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001745"&gt;Best practices in
Scientific
Computing&lt;/a&gt;.)
What's more, when they submit papers for review, only the polished
output of these programs is considered, a nice shiny figure with some
significance levels, usually from a black-box statistical routine.
Needless to say there are a great many things that can go awry between
raw data and the shiny figure, and it is a safe bet that many, many bugs
are hiding in the analyses of many, many, papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months of working on this project on and off---and
thankfully only finding one minor error in the original code, that
probably doesn't require a retraction---it is ready: A &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org"&gt;Jupyter
Notebook&lt;/a&gt;, written in Python 3, with interactive
web-based plots (in &lt;a href="http://bokeh.pydata.org/en/latest/"&gt;Bokeh&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://plot.ly"&gt;Plotly&lt;/a&gt;), version controlled, and available in a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/Composite_methods_LC13"&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt; (with
all the dependent data). I also included my
&lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/downloads"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; environment information,
detailing the required dependencies (and versions) to run the code as it
was intended. And, as a final touch of black-magic, the whole repo can
be run in the cloud via the excellent &lt;a href="http://mybinder.org"&gt;Binder
project&lt;/a&gt;! Put another way, anyone can either
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-clone"&gt;clone&lt;/a&gt; the repo and run the code
locally, or they can simply visit the repo and launch a Jupyter session
from Binder's cloud service and explore the code without even having
Python installed on their machines. Fantastic!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the reason I went to the trouble of investing time in an old
paper is because I think the value of the type of science I am doing
lies in its communication. The easier it is for people to get into the
nuts-and-bolts of what I have done, to play and experiment with these
ideas, the easier it is for them to adapt it to their own work and build
upon it. I feel that I would much rather spend time making sure my old
work does not become useless to the community, rather than simply
steam-roll on towards new research, trying to notch up as many
publications as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student only \~6 years ago, no one ever spoke to me about Open
Science, or any of the technologies that make so feasible now. I was
aware of people starting to use R from on-line message boards, although
I was encouraged to work in IDL. I was essentially given a print-out of
basic commands, access to a shared floating licence (one shared by the
whole department), and sent on my way. I had virtually no awareness
about scientific computing tools or reproducible Science. Hence my road
towards creating work like this was long, and much effort was certainly
wasted on ineffective/inefficient practices. Happily now, the landscape
has changed dramatically in only a short time for young researchers,
with organisations like &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software
Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; really making a difference.
Now, when I talk to new PhD students or older Professors, even if they
don't use Open Source languages or version control tools, they know they
exist, and they are seeing how invaluable computer science literacy can
be for their own research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link to the repo is
&lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/Composite_methods_LC13"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note when
launching the notebook from Binder, it may take around 30 seconds for
the notebook to load up, as it is fairly large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Journals"></category><category term="Open Science"></category></entry><entry><title>Monsoon madness</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/monsoon_mad.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-24T13:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-24T13:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2016-02-24:monsoon_mad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/monsoon_india.png" title="Original image by Jorge Chan" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story starts around 2012, when I received a request to review a
paper on solar activity and the Indian Monsoon from the journal
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advances_in_Space_Research"&gt;Advances in Space
Research&lt;/a&gt;. I
have reviewed many such papers (perhaps \~20) so this was nothing
unusual. A quick read revealed some tortured data, abused statistics,
and nonsense prose. All in all a fairly typical manuscript in its field.
A version of it can be found at &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1412.1041"&gt;ArXiv&lt;/a&gt;.
(To get some idea of why I say this is a typical paper, have a look at
Barrie Pittocks 1978 piece &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-94-009-9428-7_18?no-access=true"&gt;"Solar Cycles and the Weather: Successful
Experiments in
Autosuggestion?"&lt;/a&gt;,
although it is, unfortunately, pay-walled.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors were claiming that weak and strong Indian monsoons are
related to changes in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_ray"&gt;cosmic
rays&lt;/a&gt;: energetic particles
which ionize the atmosphere. (There is a good review
&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2009RG000282/abstract"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for those interested in background regarding their possible role in
climate.) The study took rainfall data from India and split into two
samples, representing the strongest and weakest monsoons recorded. Using
composites, they examined the linear change in cosmic rays over a period
of 5 months during their samples. The linear change in cosmic rays
during the weak and strong monsoon samples were of different sign. Based
on their observation that the cosmic ray changes during weak and strong
monsoons were 1) &lt;em&gt;anti-correlated&lt;/em&gt;, and 2) &lt;em&gt;showing high correlation
coefficient values&lt;/em&gt;. From this, they argued that cosmic rays affect the
monsoon via clouds, and also potentially impact global climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, something key for you to know about the cosmic rays: they vary with
a roughly 11-year period, as they are modulated by the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_cycle"&gt;Solar
Cycle&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately for the
authors, this means that if you extract a period of several months of
cosmic ray data from a time-series, and examine the linear trend, it
will very likely show either a decreasing or increasing tendency
depending on the phase of the Solar Cycle. If you were to randomly pick
a few periods from these data and stack them together (as the authors
did with a &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/abs/2013/01/swsc130020/swsc130020.html"&gt;composite
method&lt;/a&gt;),
you will end up with a trend depending on where the samples were taken
from in relation to the phase of the Solar Cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To simplify things, assume the cosmic rays vary like a sine wave over
11-years with no long-term trend. By looking at two small random
composite samples and examining the 5-month linear changes you more or
less have a 50:50 chance of having either an increasing or decreasing
trend. If you don't make an &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; assumption about what direction
the trends should be assigned to (e.g. that weak monsoons should
correspond to increasing cosmic rays and strong monsoons should
correspond to decreasing cosmic rays), and only care that the samples
are anti-correlated, your chance of getting a positive result is 50%.
However, if you argue that only one specific configuration of samples
with changes supports your argument, then the chance of randomly getting
this drops to 25%. So that more-or-less takes care of the
anti-correlation, as alone it is clearly not evidence of something
unusual here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But were high correlation coefficients unusual in this work? Because the
long term-changes in cosmic rays are determined by the Solar Cycle, the
correlation coefficient values from samples constructed the way they
authors made them tend to be high. In fact high-values are &lt;em&gt;the most
common type of values you can obtain from sampling the data in this
manner&lt;/em&gt;. (This is the core argument I present in &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/abs/2016/01/swsc150064/swsc150064.html"&gt;my
paper&lt;/a&gt;).
The authors made no real effort to test the probability values of these
data in detail, so they did not realise this. They simply applied an
out-of-the-box statistical test, and assumed the values were meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after pointing out this core problem with the paper in peer review
the editor for Advances in Space Research promptly rejected the paper
and thanked me. (I feel like noting that I rarely recommend straight
rejections in my reviews, I normally go out of my way to try to give
comments that will help people make a stronger analysis. Although the
more time goes on, the more empathise with
&lt;a href="http://www.nyu.edu/classes/keefer/hell/camus.html"&gt;Sisyphus&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year or more passed, and I received the same paper again from the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journal_of_Atmospheric_and_Solar-Terrestrial_Physics"&gt;Journal of Atmospheric and Solar Terrestrial
Physics&lt;/a&gt;,
unmodified, typos and all**. This is not so uncommon in small fields,
and has happened to me several times. So, I submitted my same review and
moved on thinking all would be well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(** This, and other examples, lead to my feeling that in many
instances authors are willing to put more effort into pushing articles
through journal systems than they are into the underlying science.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, despite arguments that the study was total rubbish, the editors
decided that this paper did indeed prove that the climate system has a
heart of cosmic rays and published it. (Again, If the claims of this
paper were true they would totally re-shape climate science. The editors
were happy to accept this paradigm shattering paper despite a clear
explanation of why it was total nonsense!) It didn't take too long for
the story to be repeated, e.g. on &lt;a href="http://hockeyschtick.blogspot.no/2014/12/new-paper-suggests-cosmic-rays-may.html"&gt;The Hockey
Schtick&lt;/a&gt;.
Over the course of a year, I protested heavily to the editors, and
pursued what I thought was a 'proper' recourse, publishing a direct
reply in the same journal as the original article. After a year with the
editors however, they were effectively stonewalling my efforts. I don't
want to go into the often frustrating and ridiculous details of that,
other than to say the end result was a prompt submission and acceptance
to the EDP Open Science journal &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/abs/2016/01/swsc150064/swsc150064.html"&gt;Space Weather and Space
Climate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story, which out of kindness I only subjected you to an abridged
version of, certainly taught me some hard lessons. For one, due to the
inordinate amount of time-wasted, I mostly only accept reviews from
editors/authors I personally know, to try to ensure they are genuinely
motivated and not simply looking to fill quotas, gain rewards, or
pad-CVs. I am also trying hard not to get sucked into studies that most
sane researchers could spot as junk and simply ignore. Finally, I think
more than ever that publishing papers should be seen as the start of a
process, not the end of one, and adopting reproducible Open Science
methods should be seen as crucial to research credibility.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Journals"></category><category term="Open Science"></category><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Climate"></category></entry><entry><title>New book launched: Earth's climate response to a changing Sun</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/TOSCAbook.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-10T10:29:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-11-10T10:29:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-11-10:TOSCAbook.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/TOSCA_group_web.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past 4 years, more than 80 scientists from 20 countries across
Europe have come together, in an EU-funded COST project, called
&lt;a href="http://lpc2e.cnrs-orleans.fr/~ddwit/TOSCA/TOSCA/Home.html"&gt;TOSCA&lt;/a&gt;.
These scientists came from a whole range of different backgrounds,
including Solar and Space Physicists, Climatologists and Atmospheric
Scientists, and everyone in-between. Over that time, they produced much
on the subject of natural climate forcing mechanisms, including many
meetings, workshops, training schools, short-term research grants,
original research studies, synthesis reports, special journal editions
and outreach materials. But the crown jewel of the collaboration is
their &lt;a href="http://www.files.benlaken.com/documents/flyer_Earth%20climate.pdf"&gt;newly-launched
book&lt;/a&gt;,
titled '&lt;em&gt;Earth's climate response to a changing Sun&lt;/em&gt;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work, affectionately referred to by the group as a hand-book, is a
considerable achievement. It is perhaps the first time a group of such
diverse researchers have poured a titanic effort into discussing at both
great length and detail, across discipline boundaries, the role of the
Sun on Earth's climate, considering cutting-edge data and hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years it has been very gratifying to watch as these researchers
have come to common ground, evolving their ideas through collaboration,
exchange and comradery, until they hit intellectual bedrock. That is
really what the book represents: the hard-boiled core of the subject,
written to be the most comprehensive and agreed-upon synthesis of this
overwhelming and exciting field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am personally sad that TOSCA has essentially disbanded and the
project is over, I am ecstatic at the achievements of the group which
they have distilled and calcified into their book. It was a pleasure to
be part of their group, which gave me many opportunities for developing
my research. To see my contribution to the book have a look at Chapter
4.7, written with &lt;a href="http://oh.geof.unizg.hr/index.php/about-hvar-observatory/staff/jasa"&gt;Dr. Jasa
Calogovic&lt;/a&gt;,
and modified with feedback from by Professors &lt;a href="http://www.mn.uio.no/geo/english/people/aca/metos/jegill/"&gt;Jon-Egil
Kristjansson&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=""&gt;Yoav Yair&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://pierce.atmos.colostate.edu"&gt;Jeffrey Pierce&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="http://www.utdallas.edu/physics/tinsley-brian/"&gt;Brian Tinsley&lt;/a&gt;. I will
likely post a synthesis of this material in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the book, or to place and order, check out
&lt;a href="http://www.files.benlaken.com/documents/flyer_Earth%20climate.pdf"&gt;the
flyer&lt;/a&gt;.
Or for more things TOSCA, drop by their &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCY8dL-P9JtEj6ulpFM0sO2w"&gt;Youtube
channel&lt;/a&gt; and
see their videos, or follow them on Twitter
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ghost_tosca"&gt;@ghost_TOSCA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="TOSCA"></category><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Climate"></category></entry><entry><title>Can PERICLES stop data fading into the ether?</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/Pericles_update.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-06T13:35:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-11-06T13:35:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-11-06:Pericles_update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/old_machine.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently attended a one-day evaluation workshop for the &lt;a href="http://pericles-project.eu"&gt;PERCICLES
Project&lt;/a&gt; as an invited reviewer. PERICLES
(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PericlesFP7"&gt;#periclesfp7&lt;/a&gt;) stands for &lt;em&gt;Promoting and Enhancing Reuse of Information
throughout the Content Lifecycle taking account of Evolving Semantics&lt;/em&gt;.
The aim was to give feedback and suggestions on the projects progress
and how they could meet their goals. The meeting was hosted at the
Belgium Institute for Space Aeronomy, in Brussels, and it took place on
29th October, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some very interesting/impressive people in attendance, and I
would say that it was an excellent opportunity for me to consider an
aspect of Open Science that I think is critical, but perhaps often
over-looked: While a frequent goal of Open Science is to be reproducible
and accessible, the need for preservation strategies are not so clearly
articulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perservation Science is certainly a whole scientific field in its own
right. In researching this subject in preparation for the workshop and
listening to the presenters, I now think that the Open Science movement
should explicitly encourage an understanding of long-term data
preservation as part of its goal of ensuring long-term reproducibility.
This would including educating researchers and encouraging them as to
proper data documentation practices, encouraging the use of open
formats, integrity checks, authors selecting proper rights to the data,
and being responsible for some type of archival strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking after the workshop with the co-investigator of the project &lt;a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/people/research/waddington/index.aspx"&gt;Dr.
Simon
Waddington&lt;/a&gt;
was particularly illuminating, and I now certainly hope that PERICLES
can succeed in impacting practices in the Scientific community. When I
think back over my own experience, it is very true that I have seen
large amounts of time and energy be wasted, essentially being trapped in
the past, through format or hardware obsolescence. (Indeed, my PhD
supervisor once gave me some &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetic_tape_data_storage#/media/File:Largetape.jpg"&gt;reels of magnetic
tape&lt;/a&gt;,
relics of research past, effectivley useless now except as
paperweights.) This is of course compounded by software development
practices which don't consider portability or even attempt to be
comprehensible to future users!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully projects like PERICLES can help to break the status-quo that
"&lt;em&gt;Digital information lasts forever--or five years--whichever comes
first&lt;/em&gt;" (Jeff Rothenberg, 1999).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Open Science"></category><category term="Reproducibility"></category></entry><entry><title>Research trip to Croatia, 2015</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/croatia-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-22T08:44:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-22T08:44:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-09-22:croatia-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Ben_Jasa.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have just returned from a research trip in Croatia (8--19th
September), with my friend and long-time collaborator &lt;a href="http://oh.geof.unizg.hr/index.php/about-hvar-observatory/staff/jasa"&gt;Dr. Jasa
Calogovic&lt;/a&gt;.
Every now-and-then Jasa and I manage to have some schedule overlap for a
collaborative trip: This time, he kindly put my wife and I up the
beautiful &lt;a href="http://oh.geof.unizg.hr"&gt;Hvar Observatory&lt;/a&gt;, which is built
around (and inside of) a Napoleonic Fortress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of the trip was Sun: from the Sun-kissed Adriatic island,
Jasa's Solar observatory, to the research itself. Apart from taking some
time to develop future project strategies we wrote a synthesis paper,
tentatively titled &lt;em&gt;Reflections on the late Cosmoclimatology&lt;/em&gt;, which we
hope will appear in the Central European Astrophysical Bulletin. The
piece briefly outlines the state the field of Sun-Earth links today in
relation to some of the grander claims over the past (roughly) 20 years,
and where future research lines are likely to yield interesting
discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also made a final check after copy-editing of our contribution to
&lt;a href="http://lpc2e.cnrs-orleans.fr/~ddwit/TOSCA/TOSCA/Home.html"&gt;TOSCA's&lt;/a&gt;
forthcoming book, which will be called &lt;em&gt;Earth's climate response to a
changing Sun&lt;/em&gt;, the book has 61 authors, and was coordinated by
Professors Jean Lilensten, Thierry Dudock de Wit, and Katja Matthes, to
be published by EDP sciences. It looks great, and a lot of hard work
went into it. I will write a more detailed post in the future when it is
finally available.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Climate"></category><category term="TOSCA"></category><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>Scientist, opine thyself</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/Opine-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-12T08:45:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-08-12T08:45:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-08-12:Opine-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/advc.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The issue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists as advocates. Should Scientists step outside of their
archetypal roles as dispassionate investigators of the physical world,
taking time away from asking questions of how things are, and instead
offer opinions on how they think things should be? Is this a moral
obligation? Or is it simply dangerous irresponsible territory beyond
their purview? Should we just be good little investigators and know our
place? Or in fact, are these the wrong questions to ask, devoid of the
nuance and perhaps ironically implying that even needing to ask it begs
only the answer, 'when you grow up'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Cosmos, Carl Sagan, and later his spiritual successor, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/neiltyson?lang=en"&gt;Neil deGrasse
Tyson&lt;/a&gt;, both passionately
discussed not only scientific facts but also issues of contemporary
importance. For Carl Sagan, who made the original Cosmos during the Cold
War, the main issue of the day was nuclear proliferation. While more
recently, Neil deGrasse Tyson rightly honed in on the dangers of
environmental damage and Climate Change. This is advocacy, no two ways
about it, but what does that really entail, and what kind of discussion
is currently going on in the climate community about advocacy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is advocacy?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 2013 &lt;a href="http://www.realclimate.org/index.php/archives/2013/12/agu-talk-on-science-and-advocacy/#ITEM-16540-0"&gt;AGU
talk&lt;/a&gt;
Professor Gavin Schmidt of NASA states that advocacy is 'the defence of
your value positions'. The idea is that a scientist has a factual view
of reality, arrived at through the scientific method and the portion of
accumulated scientific knowledge of which they are aware. This
information is mixed with our own personal biases and leads us to arrive
at a set of values we perceive to be important. Advocacy is then an
expression of these values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I note that Gavin's talk mainly revolves around the ideas of the late
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Schneider"&gt;Professor Stephen
Schneider&lt;/a&gt;, a profound
thinker on this subject. For those interested in reading more on this
topic, his work &lt;a href="http://stephenschneider.stanford.edu/Publications/PDF_Papers/Oxymoron1.pdf"&gt;Science advocate an
Oxymoron?&lt;/a&gt;
is a must.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another definition, following the article of &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1523-1739.2009.01250.x/abstract"&gt;Nelson and Vucetich
(2009)&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;On Advocacy by Environmental Scientists: What, Whether, Why, and How”&lt;/em&gt;,
argues that we may consider all communication of science not expressly
for relaying our work to colleagues a form of advocacy. So any
popularization of science (like &lt;a href="http://www.iflscience.com"&gt;I Fucking Love
Science&lt;/a&gt;) is advocacy, just in an
uncontroversial form. The type of advocacy that is controversial, and is
the kind I wish to discuss, is defined by Nelson and Vucetich as
'promoting, developing, or assessing policy positions'. Given this, as
&lt;a href="http://bigthink.com/age-of-engagement/do-scientists-have-a-special-responsibility-to-engage-in-political-advocacy"&gt;Nelson
explains&lt;/a&gt;,
the more appropriate question is not, if advocacy is appropriate, but
&lt;em&gt;"which kinds of advocacy are acceptable and, most importantly, how
ought we to go about advocacy and how ought we as a scientific community
react to advocacy"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some recent views&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been clear voices against advocacy however, particularly in
relation to the climate community, often centring around arguments of
bias, impartiality, and ethics that suggest it is problematic for
scientists to express views beyond communicating their science. Such
ideas can be found in one form or another in &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/jul/31/climate-scientists-policies"&gt;a Guardian article by
Tasmin
Edwards&lt;/a&gt;,
or many others including &lt;a href="https://dougmcneall.wordpress.com/2014/01/30/why-i-dont-advocate-for-climate-science-policy/"&gt;Doug
McNeall&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.eenews.net/stories/1059993695"&gt;Virginia Burkett&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="http://judithcurry.com/2013/12/22/rethinking-climate-advocacy/"&gt;Judith
Curry&lt;/a&gt;.
Even Brian Cox, someone I much admire as a science communicator, has
clearly stated that scientists should not advocate (e.g. see 15:46 of
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?t=952&amp;amp;v=CJC1phPS6IA"&gt;Gavin's video&lt;/a&gt;), and
has also stated that &lt;em&gt;"Advocacy has damaged trust in the science"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the Royal Society has had issues with the idea that advocacy should
not be part of science, with a group of 43 members, led by &lt;a href="http://www.desmogblog.com/andrew-montford"&gt;Andrew
Montford&lt;/a&gt;, attacking the
outspoken stance of their leaders on climate change. The dissenting
members published a report in 2012 entitled &lt;a href="http://www.thegwpf.org/images/stories/gwpf-reports/montford-royal_society.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nullus in
verba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(the motto of the Society, which I take as simply an admonishment to
remain sceptical). The report essentially chided the society for
straying away from what they saw as pure science, arguing that the
society has lost its way by engaging in advocacy. It is certainly true
that the RS has somewhat cornered itself by advertising in The
Philosophical Transactions (1753) that &lt;em&gt;"...it is an established rule of
the Society, to which they will always adhere, never to give their
opinion as a Body upon any subject either of Nature or Art, that comes
before them"&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps this is a case where a 262 year old idea doesn't
perfectly map onto the modern era, or something crazy like that. (I
would certainly not criticize the RS for being out of date in general
though, as, to my mind they are doing great work in encouraging Open
Science, and I am personally very excited to see how their new &lt;a href="http://rsos.royalsocietypublishing.org"&gt;Open
Science journal&lt;/a&gt; will develop.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, Montford's group are dancing around the idea that advocacy
puts the credibility of organizations and scientists at risk. A
&lt;a href="http://www.sheffieldscienceinpolicy.com/blog/should-scientists-be-advocates-by-dr-aaron-thierry"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;
by Dr Aaron Thierry offers a point that ideologically opposes this which
I agree with, that it is in-fact bad science, not advocacy, that
threatens trust in scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either-way, the facts on the ground show clearly that the majority of
public and also scientists support scientists voicing their opinions: &lt;a href="http://www.people-press.org/2009/07/09/section-4-scientists-politics-and-religion/"&gt;A
Pew Research Poll in
2009&lt;/a&gt;
showed that a large majority of the public in the USA (76%), and nearly
all scientists (97%), think that it is appropriate for scientists to
become actively involved in political debates on controversial issues.
Despite these numbers I think that there is still disagreement in the
community as to what manner and extent of advocacy is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The personal element&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of what the dialogue between scientists looks like on
this topic for example you can see this twitter conversation &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ClimateOfGavin/status/344458000091713538"&gt;from Gavin
Schmidt&lt;/a&gt;.
Speaking from experience I would say that most climate scientists are
motivated by much more than just scientific curiosity. Many are at their
heart idealists, motivated by a wish to create a sustainable future for
mankind and ensure a biodiverse and healthy planet. So the idea that
climate scientists should concern themselves only with carrying out and
reporting research, not attempting to participate and shape public and
political discussions seems incompatible with this idealism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An obvious but key point is that scientists are citizens, and as &lt;a href="http://bigthink.com/age-of-engagement/do-scientists-have-a-special-responsibility-to-engage-in-political-advocacy"&gt;Nelson
states in an
interview&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;"...citizens in a democracy have a moral obligation to actively promote
within their society that which they are justified in thinking is right
or good and to actively opposing that which they are justified in
thinking is wrong or bad. Consequently, because they are citizens, every
scientist has an obligation to be just and transparently honest
advocates."&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson goes on to capture the essence of what I previously mentioned
when I said that personal bias interacts with scientific understanding
(and vice versa) to shape our values and advocacy, when he states: &lt;em&gt;"If
I admittedly and intrinsically value that which I study, and if in my
study of it I discover threats to it, I think the leap to my willingness
to act on its behalf is hardly a leap at all."&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The damage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the harm with advocacy anyway? In my own background, I was
exposed to the idea that advocacy is a form of bias -- a lack of
impartiality -- and is consequently antithetical to Science. Moreover,
as I mentioned worries have been voiced that advocacy damages the
reputation of scientists in general. But I see this as a non-issue: to a
scientist, bias has a specific meaning, markedly different from everyday
use. In the world of science, impartial means limiting bias in
experimental design and analysis, an integral process in science.
Carefully designing hypothesis and experiments so that we, 'don't fool
ourselves', as &lt;a href="http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/r/richardpf137642.html"&gt;Richard Fenymann (approximately) put
it&lt;/a&gt;.
However, in common use, and particularly in relation to divided
political issues, to be impartial means something else entirely:
neutrality. These definitions are not compatible, and conflating them
through linguistic sleight is a mistake, because it is fantasy to think
that scientists are neutral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;a href="https://www.skepticalscience.com/global-warming-scientific-consensus.htm"&gt;overwhelming
majority&lt;/a&gt;
of climate scientists who agree with the conclusions of the IPCC, I
would not for a moment believe that they are impartial with regards to
questions of emission regulation or divestment in non-renewable
resources. On this matter &lt;a href="http://stephenschneider.stanford.edu/Publications/PDF_Papers/Oxymoron1.pdf"&gt;Stephen Schneider
said&lt;/a&gt;
that we all have value positions, and it is our responsibility to make
them conscious and explicit. Similarly, in his AGU talk, Gavin Schmidt
echoed this point, stating &lt;em&gt;'Many believe in pretence of complete
objectivity, and remain entirely neutral. Not true, how matter how hard
we strive.'&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another argument presented against advocacy implicitly appears in
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/political-science/2013/jul/31/climate-scientists-policies"&gt;Tasmin Edwards Guardian
piece&lt;/a&gt;,
relating to perceived scientific authority and the potential dangers of
promoting values from such a position. (Think of the psychological
effect of the 'authority figure in the white coat' from the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milgram_experiment"&gt;Milgrim
experiments&lt;/a&gt;.) Without
wanting to put words in her mouth, I assume that Edwards is being
cautious of coercing potentially sheep-like minds with views that she
recognizes as originating from her own values with perceived authority.
I find it hard to worry too much on this point however, as the
intentions of the climate community are to avert global catastrophe.
Thus it seems to make little difference in this case if people are
convinced out of trust/deference to a Milgrim-like authority figure, or
because they understand the physical arguments. More importantly though,
I think that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a clear and recognisable distinction between the
scientist speaking, the scientific evidence they present, and the
opinions/recommendations they give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we consider a scientist simply as a person who understands and
practices the scientific method, acknowledging that just like all people
they possess their own biases. And we consider Science itself to be the
application of critical tests to ideas with the aim of arriving at an
understanding of the material world. Then it seems quite plain that just
because a scientist speaks in a public forum, does not mean they speak
for Science (&lt;em&gt;nullus in verba&lt;/em&gt;). They can communicate the fruits of
scientific labour and comment on them, but the spectre that they may
speak with the authority of Science, forever damaging the reputation of
scientists is misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a view from the ground, my friend and colleague, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hansbrenna"&gt;Hans
Brenna&lt;/a&gt;, a climate researcher currently
investigating the role of volcanoes on stratospheric chemistry, believes
that the logical result of arguments against advocacy are a slippery
slope. Leading to the conclusion that if scientists are unable to
advocate based on their understanding of scientific results and their
own values, then no experts or person with competence in a field should
be allowed to advocate based on their understanding of that field. He
argues that this creates nonsensical results, making enlightened
advocacy and public debate impossible. He suggests that the origin of
this objection is most beneficial to a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_change_denial"&gt;general PR campaign against
climate
scientists&lt;/a&gt;,
encouraging politicians and public alike to ignore the advice of climate
science. Hans says &lt;em&gt;"I'm afraid that if it succeeds on us, it will be
brought to bear on other controversial topics in the future"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from being unrealistic, general calls to limit the advocacy of
scientists may be detrimental or even destructive, by encouraging the
removal of the voices of people who have the clearest understanding of
the world and climate change from the public discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final example, let's say you were sitting in a burning house, but
for some reason you are unsure if the house is really burning (perhaps
too much Descartes before bed). You call a scientist, who promptly
arrives to determine if the house really is on fire. After doing the
appropriate test, the scientist tells you that with a &amp;gt;99.9%
probability the house, is, indeed on fire. He then hastens to add you
should leave before you burn alive, as he considers that this would be
undesirable. The difference between the scientific conclusion, and the
policy advice should be clear. Is it inherently problematic for the
scientist to suggest a course of action? Or rather, is it their moral
imperative if they believe that your burning alive would be a bad thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that only a moral relativist could object to the above, as it
would require arguing that it is wrong to assume simply because the
scientist in my story does not wish to burn alive that they presume you
would also value this outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After considering this issue, I would say that the question of should
scientists advocate is invalid, as, unless we wish to communicate via
raw data, advocacy in some form is unavoidable. After acknowledging that
all scientists are individually free to advocate or not as they wish,
the real question is how to do so responsibly and ethically. I believe
this comes down to the individuals making their value judgements clear.
Again, Professor Stephen Schneider has already &lt;a href="http://stephenschneider.stanford.edu/Publications/PDF_Papers/Oxymoron1.pdf"&gt;lucidly outlined these
points&lt;/a&gt;
years ago.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Communication"></category><category term="Advocacy"></category><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>A conversational climate</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/discussion-posts.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-23T16:16:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-07-23T16:16:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-07-23:discussion-posts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/conv_clim.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post differs from my usual fare as it follows the format of an FAQ
of sorts. For me, it is representative of a conversation I have had a
number of times now. I have found that the points raised are usually
asked of me by people of a right-leaning political persuasion with some
background knowledge of climate. But first some brief back-story to
explain how this came about...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently the &lt;a href="http://lpc2e.cnrs-orleans.fr/~ddwit/TOSCA/TOSCA/Home.html"&gt;TOSCA
group&lt;/a&gt; posted
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtRPfc5zKNI"&gt;a series of short videos on
YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, where they
discussed their research in the field of Sun-Earth links for a general
audience. They also re-posted &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtRPfc5zKNI"&gt;my
video&lt;/a&gt;. This ended with the
conclusion that I am &lt;em&gt;'certain that the hypothesis which states the Sun
is responsible for the majority of recent global warming via a link
between cosmic radiation and clouds, is false'&lt;/em&gt;. (It is interesting to
note that I think most researchers would at this point find this
conclusion obvious and not at all controversial, while a small number
may find it inflammatory.) I also closed by saying that despite this,
there are still many open and interesting questions in the field of
solar-terrestrial research. After gaining a few views, a comment was
posted on the video to which I wrote a reply. There followed a series of
questions and replies, which I thought would be useful to write up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should preface this with the disclaimer that due to the nature of a
free-flowing conversation large parts of this material stray outside my
own area of active research, particularly towards the end. I have also
not posted the original questions verbatim (which you can &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtRPfc5zKNI"&gt;read
here&lt;/a&gt;), but rather I have
simplified and shortened them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: How can you say you are "certain" that cosmic rays aren't the cause of global warming - I thought certainty was unscientific?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that even our most well-tested hypotheses are only
technically described as theories, not fact. This is down to the nature
of a scientific hypothesis, they can only be disproven or withstand
scrutiny, not positively proven. With this in mind, in my video I end by
saying I am certain that a specific hypothesis has failed. I refer to
the hypothesis that the Sun, via cosmic rays, is a principle driver of
climate and a primary cause of recent climate change (see Svensmark's
'Cosmoclimatology' &lt;a href="http://astrogeo.oxfordjournals.org/content/48/1/1.18.extract"&gt;paper
here&lt;/a&gt; to
read this idea in its original form). As the aforementioned hypothesis
is making a testable knowledge claim, it is open to exacting scrutiny
(it is this very quality that makes it a scientific hypothesis). So,
although the scientific method cannot positively prove something, we may
test it and perhaps disprove it. Currently, the hypothesis has failed a
wide range of independent tests and can be considered thoroughly
defunct. So while scientists may not say with definitive certainty they
are sure something is true, they may say if specific claims are not
true! In the same vein we could say we are certain the Flat-Earth
hypothesis has failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: I thought this cosmic ray-global warming hypothesis was a new idea: how can you dismiss it so readily?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of Solar-Climate connections is very old (perhaps first
appearing in scientific literature by William Herschel more than 200
years ago). The idea that it is cosmic rays specifically that affect the
Earth's weather is younger however, to my knowledge having been &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v183/n4659/abs/183451a0.html"&gt;first
proposed in 1959 by Edward
Ney&lt;/a&gt;.
Some of the first suggestions of a mechanism for this link were along
the lines of cosmic-rays induced atmospheric electricity and cloud
droplets (&lt;a href="http://figshare.com/articles/Does_Europe_s_wind_respond_to_either_ENSO_or_the_Solar_cycle_/1471639"&gt;R.E. Dickinson,
1975&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364682697000011"&gt;Sevensmark and Friis-Christensen
(1997)&lt;/a&gt;
first reported that satellite measurements of clouds showed evidence of
this, to a sufficient degree to explain large portions of global warming
as a natural phenomenon. But, as I discussed in &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/abs/2012/01/swsc120049/swsc120049.html"&gt;an open-access
paper&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://ccrg2013.blogspot.co.uk/2013/04/blog-entry-of-ben-laken-april-2013.html?view=timeslide"&gt;an earlier
post&lt;/a&gt;,
these observations did not hold weight, and over the last approximately
20 years, many researchers have examined this claim through various
independent methods, finding significant problems and null results. I
myself have looked primarily at large-scale satellite observations to
explore this idea (for example
&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2011GL049764/abstract;jsessionid=DFB5CE34983D36916606DFB0305E2483.f03t03?wol1URL=/doi/10.1029/2011GL049764/abstract&amp;amp;regionCode=ES&amp;amp;identityKey=1ed243b7-f978-42d9-82a1-f0e0d33fa9d4&amp;amp;isReportingDone=false"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href="http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/JCLI-D-11-00306.1"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;),
which show null results in terms of changes that could be significant to
global warming. Cumulatively, this weight of evidence has led mainstream
climate scientists to reject the idea of a significant cosmic ray cloud
link, as outlined in &lt;a href="http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/assessment-report/ar5/wg1/WG1AR5_Chapter07_FINAL.pdf"&gt;Chapter
7&lt;/a&gt;
Section 4.6 (page 613) of the IPCC fifth assessment report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: What about the politics of the science and scientists: isn't it true that this is some kind of mainstream climate-cult/conspiracy, wherein people who propose new ideas counter to mainstream views are automatically demonised and painted as 'climate deniers'?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have only made statements regarding ideas, not people. As far as I am
concerned original thinking, constrained by reason and evidence, and
open discussion should be valued in science. For another perspective on
this field and its denizens, read the very &lt;a href="http://www.eenews.net/stories/1059974149"&gt;interesting article by
journalist Paul Voosen&lt;/a&gt;. My
statement of certainty regarding the falsehood of the cosmic ray--Global
warming hypothesis is not a political one: it is purely based on
evidence. That is not to say I don't have my own opinions and biases
(like everyone), but in this case the hypothesis has failed numerous
independent tests. That is the only relevant point, and the only reason
for discarding it. The political aspect of this topic is a very
different conversation, and for me the interesting question regarding
the politics of climate science is actually the inverse of the above: it
regards how disproportionate amounts of power, support, and reporting
have been given to the minuscule number of so-called 'climate deniers'.
It is both angering and motivating that for each clear message from the
scientific community the 'deniers' calcified and pushed back, surely
contributing to the delay of meaningful international action, as
described in the book &lt;a href="http://www.merchantsofdoubt.org"&gt;The Merchants of
Doubt&lt;/a&gt;. (A fact attested to by
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2014/nov/17/climate-change-denial-scepticism-republicans-congress"&gt;politicians apparent acceptance of
charlatans&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://www.skepticalscience.com/skepticquotes.php"&gt;debunked myths&lt;/a&gt;
as the basis to reject the science of climate change.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: But what about the Little Ice age in Medieval Europe: it correlates to a period of unusually low solar activity called a Grand Minimum. Is this not a big hint the Sun is important to climate?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may well be solar related mechanisms of regional importance worth
investigating, likely related to dynamics. I have even recently done
some work on this myself, regarding 200 years of regional weather
conditions and solar phase. (This is currently under review, and I will
write a blog post on it if/when it is accepted, although you can already
view the work as an &lt;a href="http://figshare.com/articles/Does_Europe_s_wind_respond_to_either_ENSO_or_the_Solar_cycle_/1471639"&gt;IPython notebook on
figshare&lt;/a&gt;.)
As I mentioned at the end of my video, there is still much work to be
done, and discounting the aforementioned cosmic ray-climate change
hypothesis doesn't close the door on many interesting solar-terrestrial
pathways which may indeed impact regional climate variability. TOSCA has
produced a book, which will be shortly published, summarising the large
body of interdisciplinary work in this field which is ongoing. A key
point however, is that regional climate variability is most certainly
not the same thing as global climate change, for more on this
distinction in relation to solar forcing see &lt;a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/1748-9326/5/2/021001/pdf/1748-9326_5_2_021001.pdf"&gt;Benestad
2010&lt;/a&gt;.
It essentially means that the interest in the role of the Sun is on
processes that affect regional-scale variability, not global trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: Despite what you have said about the Sun not impacting climate change, isn't it true that Scientists don't understand everything about the climate? And if so, how can they be so sure we should make policy changes?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As made crystal clear by the efforts of the IPCC, the science is settled
and has been for a long time with regard to having sufficient
information for policy makers to go out and make positive changes. (Of
course, this itself is a bit exasperating, as the old joke goes, the
politician stands up and asks &lt;em&gt;"What if Climate Change is all a hoax and
we make a better world for nothing?"&lt;/em&gt;). Unfortunately, I would say the
clarity of the climate science community, despite earning a Nobel prize,
has proved largely irrelevant. Why is this? Well, perhaps you will think
this cynical, but I would say that the explanation for this failure can
be caricatured thusly: When policy-makers want support for a given
action, they call upon an 'expert' to offer scientific rational. But
inversely, if particular scientific conclusions are contrary to a
desired policy, they will ask their expert source &lt;em&gt;"is everything about
this understood?"&lt;/em&gt;, to which the scientist will diligently and
invariably answer &lt;em&gt;"No, of course we don't understand everything"&lt;/em&gt;. This
is just the nature of science, but nuances like that have a habit of
leeching out of a public debate. At this point, the trap is sprung and
the conclusion is &lt;em&gt;"Well, we simply cant do anything before we can be
100% sure. More research is needed before action can be taken."&lt;/em&gt;. Again,
this is just a simplification, and is only one of many tactics to take
the clarity out of a scientific argument, but it is suitably
illustrative to show that scientific findings alone are often lame to
drive policy changes. These themes are explored in detail in &lt;a href="http://www.merchantsofdoubt.org"&gt;The
Merchants of Doubt&lt;/a&gt;, and I would
recommend you read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Q: But what about climate models: I don't believe they are accurate 100 years into the future, and they seem to be doing a bad job now. How can we base policy on models we can't trust?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well one thing to keep in mind is the models are statistically
projecting future climate states, not predicting future weather. I think
many of them don't capture sub-decade time-scale variability well, such
as that arising from internal oscillations in complex systems. So it
isn't really a big issue to my mind that the model predictions deviate
from observations for what seems to us to be relatively long periods.
(Although I may well be mistaken here, as climate models are not my
field.) They are certainly an imperfect tool, missing,
miss-representing, and are even inherently incapable of reproducing some
processes. But despite that, they are also still the best tool we have
for projecting the future consequences of our emissions. In particular,
we should pay attention to where there is clear agreement between the
models. For example, all models show the majority of surface will warm
significantly over the next century, and experience intense and more
frequent heat-waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real message of the models for me anyway, is not the small details a
century into the future--which depending on the exact parameter may be
quite uncertain--but the message that continued anthropogenic emissions
(and the energy imbalance we have already created) will significantly
alter the climate system in a way that makes it more hostile for human
civilization. This really is bad news for a species that depends on the
current status quo of the climate for agriculture and resource
management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine that it is the changing probability of extreme events, and
patterns of variability that will be the primary problem for human
civilisation: Years of successive extreme events in key areas for people
and resources, made more likely by anthropogenic climate forcings, will
be far more dangerous to existing global economic social and political
systems than the relatively slow change in global mean conditions a
century from now. (Although the flooding of coastlines and
ocean-acidification will surely take their toll in due course.) The
aforementioned human socio-economic systems have already demonstrated
their fragility and inter-connectedness for example during the recent
global financial crisis: even climatologists studying ENSO must stop and
marvel at the teleconnections that cause a property speculation in the
USA to be linked to global economic shock waves. To my mind at least,
the most immediate global danger of climate change is to add a
potentially destabilising wild card to global socio-economic systems.
Albeit, a wild card that scientists have been clearly warning society
about now for several decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write the final lines of this post, James Hansen and others have
&lt;a href="http://www.atmos-chem-phys-discuss.net/15/20059/2015/acpd-15-20059-2015.pdf"&gt;just posted in ACPD a
paper&lt;/a&gt;
that makes a similar point in far more exacting way, so I will close by
citing a paragraph from their conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Our analysis paints a different picture than IPCC (2013) for how this
Hyper-Anthropocene phase is likely to proceed if GHG emissions grow at a
rate that continues to pump energy at a high rate into the ocean. We
conclude that multi-meter sea level rise would become practically
unavoidable. Social disruption and economic consequences of such large
sea level rise could be devastating. It is not difficult to imagine that
conflicts arising from forced migrations and economic collapse might
make the planet ungovernable, threatening the fabric of civilization."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Climate"></category><category term="Science"></category></entry><entry><title>TOSCA launches short YouTube documentary series</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/TOSCA_documentaries.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-07-17:TOSCA_documentaries.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TOSCA has just launched a series of short documentaries summarising the work we have been doing over the past few years on their &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCY8dL-P9JtEj6ulpFM0sO2w"&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. My contribution is embedded below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/qtRPfc5zKNI'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="TOSCA"></category><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Climate"></category><category term="YouTube"></category></entry><entry><title>Evidence the solar cycle affects human fertility and life-span?</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/solarcycle_human_fertility.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-15T05:31:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-06-15T05:31:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-06-15:solarcycle_human_fertility.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="alt text" src="./images/solar_death.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year some colleagues emailed around the latest paper
claiming a strong causal relationship between the solar cycle and some
Earth-bound phenomena, in this case the fertility and lifetime of people
born during different phases of the solar cycle in Norway from historic
records. Usually, such studies are cause for some mirth, and make for
useful examples of common statistical problems, see for example the
relationship between &lt;a href="http://www.academicjournals.org/article/article1380707205_Verma.pdf"&gt;cosmic rays and car
crashes&lt;/a&gt;,
or &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364682602000329"&gt;heart attacks and the solar
cycle&lt;/a&gt;.
The study was carried out by a group of Norwegian researchers and
published in the prestigious Proceedings of the Royal Society B, and
could be considered to be a confirmation study as it notes that it is
supported by earlier findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is &lt;a href="http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/282/1801/20142032"&gt;"Solar activity at birth predicted infant survival and
women's fertility in historical
Norway"&lt;/a&gt;,
by &lt;a href="http://www.ntnu.no/ansatte/gine.skjarvo"&gt;Gine Roll Skjærvø†&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.ntnu.edu/employees/frode.fossoy"&gt;Frode
Fossøy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.ntnu.no/ansatte/eivin.roskaft"&gt;Eivin
Røskaft&lt;/a&gt; of the Department of
Biology, Norwegian University of Science and Technology (NTNU), in
Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being of a sceptical orientation I of course wished to see the data for
myself, as did numerous others. So followed an interesting email
exchange with the authors and several other researchers who were all
eager to sink their teeth into the original data. At first the authors
were very reticent to share their code and data, and they were
apparently unaware that Proc. Roy. Soc. B has a &lt;a href="http://royalsocietypublishing.org/data-sharing"&gt;policy regarding open
access&lt;/a&gt;, which is summed
up as "the right to read is the right to mine". It means that any
analysis published in their journal must support open code and data, and
so after this was pointed out to the authors, they shortly sent out a
version of their data and R code. Which you too can download exactly as
I received it
&lt;a href="http://www.files.benlaken.com/documents/Solar_Norway_orignal_files.zip"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
If you struggle to reproduce all their results from these files alone
however you will not be alone, and I suggest you can &lt;a href="mailto:roskaft@bio.ntnu.no"&gt;email Prof. Eivin
Roskaft directly&lt;/a&gt; for further explanation
and potentially missing data/code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper has received relatively high-amounts of attention and been
absorbed into news networks and social media. You can see the paper is
in the top 5% of articles in the
&lt;a href="http://www.altmetric.com/details/3043510"&gt;Altmetrics&lt;/a&gt; system, and ranks
in the 97th percentile of attention for articles published around the
same time. So, what are the claims of the article to warrant such
attention?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study analysed Church records from Norway between 1676 and 1878,
examining features such as recorded births and deaths. The authors
reached several strong conclusions, such as being born during solar
minimum reduces the likelihood of surviving to adulthood by cutting
human lifespan by 5.2 years. The authors essentially proposed that this
was due to higher levels of UVB received by unborn babies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at solar-correlation studies, I often find that many are a
quagmire of messy logic, so much so that it is difficult to know where
to start assessing their validity. Personally, I like to go straight for
the core finding, the most significant result, and work outward from
there. If there is a problem with the core result, then I will consider
the study in error and stop, if not I will keep going until all claims
withstand scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper one of the most purportedly statistically significant
claims is that solar activity is significantly related to the number of
children born (fertility) in lower-class women, with these women bearing
on average 0.14 less children during the solar maximum than during the
solar minimum (p=0.027). This relationship did not hold true for the
higher-class women. The sample of lower-class women was drawn from 621
individuals over 162 years, while the upper-class women sample was drawn
from 1222 individuals over 202 years. These results are shown below, and
are a bar chart comparison of the mean fertility (with some uncertainty
estimate) for upper (wealthy) and lower (poor) class women in Norway.
Indeed, the upper-class women have a similar fertility in years of solar
maximum and solar minimum, while the lower-class women show a seemingly
clear difference in the mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Norway_solar_fig2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fertility (mean + s.e.) in relation to solar activity for men and for
women in relation to socio-economic status. *p , 0.05. Dark grey bars
denote SSmax, light grey bars denote SSmin. &lt;a href="http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/282/1801/20142032"&gt;adapted from Figure
2.&lt;/a&gt;
Now, I don't wish to be disparaging of fellow researchers, however,
there are common stereotypes in science that Biologists on the whole
have some issues with statistics and reproducible results (for example
see
&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/irreproducible-biology-research-costs-put-at-28-billion-per-year-1.17711"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
or
&lt;a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/fire-in-the-mind/2014/01/29/raw-data-widespread-problem-irreproducible-results/#.VXtbTWA7Spo"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
Indeed, it does seem to be the case here that the authors have simply
run some data through an R-package without clearly understanding what is
going on, and consequently are led to what I am now confident are
unjustifiable conclusions. I say this as I have gone back over their
data and created a simple IPython Jupyter notebook (available on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/Nbks/blob/master/Historical_birth_analysis.ipynb"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;)
to see what is really going on. The details delve into a particularly
favourite topic of mine, random sampling. If you want details on the
method I use below you can find them in an open-access article of mine
published in the &lt;a href="http://www.swsc-journal.org/articles/swsc/abs/2013/01/swsc130020/swsc130020.html"&gt;Journal of Space Weather and Space
Climate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, my notebook shows the basic results of the fertility difference
are reproducible: this time instead of a simple bar-chart, I have used
notched box-plots. These show more details, in particular giving a
better idea of how similar the means of the population are, and also the
whole population distribution. The notches are in fact a statistical
test of a kind, they show the position of the mean value with a 95%
confidence. The figure shows that while the mean of the solar minimum
population is larger than at solar maximum, there is still pretty
clearly some overlap in the values. So the big question here is, how
significant are the differences in the means between the low-class
women's fertility at solar maximum &lt;em&gt;vs.&lt;/em&gt; solar minimum? In particular, I
want to know are these differences distinguishable from random samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Solar_norway_boxplots.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notched box-plots showing differences in fertility by gender, and social
class (female only) during solar minimum (blue) and solar maximum (red)
periods. See
&lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/Nbks/blob/master/Historical_birth_analysis.ipynb"&gt;Notebook&lt;/a&gt;
for more details.
Before I answer this question though, there is another important factor
to consider that should be quite a red-flag here. While the authors have
stated the original sample sizes of their groups (e.g. n = 621
lower-class women, n = 1222 upper-class women), this does not give you
any clear indication of how the samples are broken up when sub-divided
into solar maximum and minimum periods. From my box-plot I included
these numbers: You can see that for high-class women the split is 239 to
983, while for the lower-class women 125 to 496. Thus the samples are
certainly not even, and while this isn't automatically a problem (as
many statistical tests can account for this), it is a problem if you
wish to directly compare properties of the sub-samples (such as mean
values), because, as I will show below sub-sampling can result in
different distributions (particularly when the sub-samples are
relatively small).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how to see the statistical significance of the mean value? There is
an easy way with a Monte Carlo approach. It simply involves starting
from the full n = 621 group of lower-class females, and then randomly
taking a sub-sample of that population. You find the mean of that
sub-sample, make a note of it, and then repeating this procedure
over-and-over again, say 100,000 times (best not to try it by hand...).
The only complication is that you have to make sure that you are taking
a sample of the same size (n) as the one you are interested in
evaluating (in this case it means that the solar maximum and minimum
samples must have different Monte Carlo populations, as they had n = 145
and n = 496 respectively).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Solar_norway_distrib.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monte Carlo distributions of random cases drawn from the low-class women
fertility data, with sample sizes matching the solar maximum (n=125) and
solar minimum (n=496)samples. The blue lines show the mean (and
uncertainty) of the actual samples. See
&lt;a href="https://github.com/benlaken/Nbks/blob/master/Historical_birth_analysis.ipynb"&gt;Notebook&lt;/a&gt;
for more details.
So, from the Monte Carlo approach, I created two distributions of mean
values, the results of which are visible as a PDF (probability density
function) as the grey shaded regions in the above figure. These
represent the null-case, that is to say that they are the means you
could expect to get when nothing special is going on in the samples
(i.e. this is what the range of values for no relationship between solar
activity and fertility should look like). To these distributions I have
over-plotted the mean value of the samples the authors obtained (and the
uncertainty, i.e. possible range of values), shown in the blue lines.
So, you can qualitatively interpret this figure by comparing the
position of the blue lines against the grey distribution values: the
more towards the middle of the grey distribution the less unusual it is.
You see immediately that the blue range is quite large, spanning a
considerable portion of the distribution in both cases, and is not
located in the tails (unusual portions) of the distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, this shows that the solar minimum fertility of the
lower-class women (of 4.09 ±0.12) ranks in the 77.8th percentile with
upper and lower certainty values of 96.0 and 41.51 percentile
respectively compared to random samples. The Monte Carlo has shown a
Gaussian distribution fits the data, and so I can use the sigma values
to estimate probability: The average value of the solar minimum sample
has a sigma of 0.77 (with an uncertainty range between 1.76 to -0.22
sigma). This translates to a two-tailed probability value of p=0.44,
with the potential to be anywhere between p=0.08 and p=0.83. So, nothing
unusual there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar maximum sample mean (of 3.62 ±0.25) for lower-class women is
certainly more shifted to the tail of the PDF, at the 6.2th percentile,
and a upper/lower 95% certainty range of 0.4th / 30.6th percentile. This
relates to a mean sigma value of -1.53 with uncertainty over a range of
-2.56 to -0.51, relating to two-tailed probability values of p=0.13, and
an uncertainty range over p0.01 to p0.61. So while it is tending towards
significance in the most favourable estimates of the mean, it is
definitely not highly significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, these results do not support the authors claim of a highly
p&amp;lt;0.05 significant difference between fertility of low-class women at
solar maximum and minimum. As this was the strongest result presented, I
am no longer motivated to check the results further, but if you are
particularly interested to further the notebook I am happy to accept
pull-requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is interesting to note though, the authors go quite far in
their interpretation of their results, writing: "&lt;em&gt;Our findings suggest
that maternal exposure to solar activity during gestation can affect the
fitness of female children.&lt;/em&gt;" They ask, "&lt;em&gt;Why, then, is the fitness of
women more sensitive to high solar activity during early life than is
the fitness of men? First, solar activity could differentially affect
the abortion rate of male and female fetuses. If only the most robust
male fetuses survive, while all female fetuses survive, male fertility
could be less affected.&lt;/em&gt;". They go on to say "&lt;em&gt;[An] explanation for
the observed gender differences is that the development of the
reproductive organs is more costly in females than in males, and thus
more at risk for developmental abnormalities when exposed to a stressor
during organogenesis [44]. Concurrently, as the developmental period
of the reproductive organs in the two sexes is different, testicular and
ovarian organs most likely experience different hazards of in utero
exposure [44] to, for example, UVR.&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good example of how with a little data, black-box statistics,
some jargon, and a lot of imagination you can end up somewhere rather
far from Science. So, to conclude: I wouldn't suggest anyone loose sleep
worrying about having lost 5.2 years by being born during the wrong
solar phase, and I would say this is yet another example of why
manuscripts need to have code and data as visible and important as the
manuscripts themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Sun"></category><category term="Statistics"></category><category term="p-hacking"></category></entry><entry><title>Helping at the Software Carpentry course Oslo June 2--3rd</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/swc_oslo_2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-05T08:12:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-06-05T08:12:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-06-05:swc_oslo_2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/swc_oslo.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helping at the &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;
course, June 2--3rd Oslo run by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lexnederbragt"&gt;Lex
Nederbragt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, certainly gave me a
lot to consider. The two-day course taught novice users Bash, Git, and
Python (&lt;a href="https://jupyter.org"&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt;). Three invaluable and
complimentary tools which are the centre of my own work-flow. I was
excited to see how people were introduced to these tools and the
Software Carpentry teaching methods. The collaborative &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/lessons.html"&gt;Git-based lesson
materials&lt;/a&gt; are especially
nice, and I can only hope this teaching model spreads far and wide. I
certainty appreciated running through the course material, and in
particular I don't remember seeing a clearer introduction to Git and
Bash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself, I stumbled into the use of Bash, Git and Python one-by-one over
time and learned alone through a lot of trial-and-error (and Youtube)
over a relatively long period of time. So I was quite curious to see how
the students would absorb so much information so quickly, and if it
would really change the way they intend to work in the future. The
students were very competent, and I got the feeling that they quickly
realized the possibilities for these tools. In fact there was very
little for the helpers to do, as the students (and even their computers)
were all operating excellently!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Software Carpentry Information for helpers and teaching instructions
was superb, and certainly gave me a few things to consider. I had seen
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gvwilson"&gt;Greg Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, the creator of Software
Carpentry talk about some of the ideas underpinning the group on Youtube
(&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q7wyA2lbPaU"&gt;for example see here&lt;/a&gt;),
and had been meaning to follow his suggested readings on the subject of
teaching (such as &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Learning-Works-Research-Based-Principles/dp/0470484101"&gt;How learning Works by Susan Ambrose et
al&lt;/a&gt;).
Following the course recommendations about the use of language and
computer etiquette to students was a valuable experience: for example,
not using the word 'just' (as they consider that it immediately sets a
tone of inaccessibility), and not taking-over keyboards when students
run into trouble or using short-cuts to fix problems. These were quite
an adjustment at first, as without being aware of it, these actions were
definitely my default setting ("Ah, a problem? You should just do thing
x! **while I type a blur of short-cut keys**" - I can see how that
might be sub-optimal for student-learning...). So I immediately felt
making the small changes the course suggested forced me into a much more
user-friendly state for the students!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve the course though, I think that I would have tried to
emphasise some real-world use cases from the Jupyter Notebook. As, even
if the students can't understand yet how they were built, they would at
least see what is be possible. For me at least, seeing people working at
a high-level in these tools was a big motivation for self-improvement,
as I realised that these were the tools that could take your work to a
new level and were the tools worth investing time in learning. By only
presenting a simplified use cases I got the feeling that although
everyone probably left with a good handle on what was covered, perhaps
they were still largely unaware of the possibilities in Python and the
Jupyter Notebook for Open Science, which for me is the most interesting
and exciting part.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Software Carpentry"></category><category term="Teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Saharan dust over the North Atlantic</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/calima.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-29T09:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-05-29T09:48:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-05-29:calima.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Between 2010 and 2014 I was a postdoc at the Instituto de Astrofísica de
Canarias on the island of Tenerife of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canary_Islands"&gt;Canary
Archipelago&lt;/a&gt;. From time to
time, we would experience extreme climate events known locally as
Calima. These are periods where mineral dust from the Sahara, exported
in discrete and often-dramatic outbreak events, are suspended in the
air. The Calima conditions last from hours to days. During this time
dramatic changes occur in the local climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/terra.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terra MODIS false colour image of a strong Calima event over the Canary
Islands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although like most aerosols, mineral dust increases the Earth’s
reflectance of short-wave radiation, the dust also absorbs radiation –
i.e. the dust both reflects and absorbs short-wave radiation, the
specific proportions with which it does so are determined by a variety
of factors such as the angle of incidence, and surface properties of the
mineral dust grains. As a result of the dusts radiative impact, air
containing the suspended dust is hotter than it would otherwise be.
Consequently, when Calima is present, air temperature increases with
height in the troposphere, creating an inversion: normally at the
latitudes of the Canary Islands, air temperature decreases through the
troposphere until the tropopause (around 10 km above sea level). Indeed,
in the same way the temperature boundary between the troposphere and
stratosphere traps the Earth’s weather systems within the troposphere,
the miniature and localised temperature inversions associated with the
Calima trap the hot, windless air over the Canary Islands – normally a
rather unpleasant experience for their ~2,120,000 inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calima is interesting, as, far from being a phenomenon of merely
localised impacts, the transport of Saharan mineral dust westwards over
the North Atlantic (and indeed in many other directions) actually has
impacts across the globe. Perhaps of most note is the dusts role in
maintaining primary-productivity over the Amazon basin – dust from the
Sahara is a crucial fertiliser to the Amazon rainforest. The dust not
only fertilisers terrestrial photosynthesises, but also primary
productivity of oceans: algal blooms resulting from mineral dust
fertilisation are visible from space, and constitute a significant
element of the global ecosystem. There are also more diverse and curious
impacts of the dust, ranging from the creation of the ominously titled
blood-rain; to influences on soil development around the world; or
providing the rare type of particles able to act as Ice Forming Nuclei
in clouds found to be influential as far away as Alaska; the dust has
even been indirectly linked to the death of coral in the Caribbean by
providing a vector for spores producing Sea Fan disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Haboob.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dramatic Haboob over Arizona, USA - much dust is entrained over the
Sahara by similar Haboobs over Africa. These occur seasonally in
association with the movement of the Inter Tropical Discontinuity over
the Saharan region. The resulting formation of mesoscale convective
systems and associated cold tongues generates Haboobs. Image credit
Daniel Bryant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the Sahara and Sahel of North Africa is the largest source of
mineral dust, which, itself is the largest constituent of the global
aerosol burden by mass, there was relatively little known about it until
recently. This is changing following the efforts of scientists in
numerous monitoring campaigns such as SAMUM (&lt;a href="http://samum.tropos.de/"&gt;the SAharan Mineral dUst
experiMent&lt;/a&gt;) and the &lt;a href="http://fennec.ouce.ox.ac.uk/"&gt;Fennec
project&lt;/a&gt;. Following successes of such
campaigns and other studies, scientists have pinpointed key regions
important to the entrainment of dust over the Sahara, and the mechanisms
by which the dust is entrained and exported and eventually deposited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="./images/Meteosat.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The immense scale of the dust outbreaks can be appreciated from 36,000
km above the Earth, courtesy of the thermal infra-red (IR) channel from
Meteosat 3~rd~ generation satellite platform (taken on 03/03/2004). A
strong dust outbreak event is visible over North Africa as white
(relatively low IR emission) region against the darker (high IR
emission) land surface. Image from NEODAAS Dundee Satellite Receiving
Station, credit EUMETSAT/NERC/Dundee University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitoring dust export events from the Sahara can be performed by
through ground-based measurements, satellite observations, or
palaeoclimatic reconstructions. All of these methods have different
benefits and limitations. Recently, in &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/qj.2170/abstract"&gt;a
paper&lt;/a&gt;
published in the Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society,
I have used nightly optical extinction data taken from the Carlsberg
Meridian Telescope located on La Palma recorded over an approximately 30
year period to reconstruct the summertime Calima frequency experienced
at the Canary Islands. These data show that in summer months between
1983 and 1997 Calima went from occurring around 50% of the time to only
around 10% of the time; then for the remaining period of data (2000 –
2012), the summertime Calima showed no long term trend, essentially
remaining consistent around 15% of the time, with year-to-year
variations of around 20%. An update to this work should be forthcoming
with improved data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frequency of Calima events (%) during the high dust season months
(July–September),from 1984 to 2012. These data were derived from optical
extinction measurements made &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; at the Island of La Palma.
Adapted from Figure 6 of &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/qj.2170/abstract"&gt;Laken et al.
2013.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the variations in summer time Calima occurrence in relation
to a variety of climate indexes showed that the majority (~50%) of the
observed variations in summertime Calima experienced annually are linked
to changes in the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) occurring around
10-months earlier; this was likely due to a connection between the NAO
and rainfall anomalies over North Africa, as moisture reduces the amount
of dust for several reasons. Previous studies of Saharan dust outbreaks
over the Canary Islands using different datasets and focusing on other
times of the year have also shown statistical associations to the NAO.
This result is not so surprising, as it is logical that the weather over
the Atlantic should have a significant impact on the properties (e.g.
if, how, when, and where) dust may be exported from the African
continent over the North Atlantic region. However, the exact mechanisms
which link variations in the NAO 10-months earlier to summertime Calima
experienced at specific regions (such as the Canary Islands) are
currently unclear, and are certainly a subject for further study.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Aerosols"></category><category term="Climate"></category><category term="Statistics"></category><category term="Remote Sensing"></category></entry><entry><title>Changes in carbon monoxide pollution 2000–2012</title><link href="https://benlaken.com/co_pollution.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-08T09:36:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-05-08T09:36:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Benjamin Laken</name></author><id>tag:benlaken.com,2015-05-08:co_pollution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Carbon monoxide (CO) is one of 6 major air pollutants regulated by
countries such as the USA. It is a product of combustion like its
closely related cousin carbon dioxide, however, unlike carbon dioxide,
it is formed by incomplete or inefficient combustion. While carbon
dioxide is an important greenhouse gas contributing to human-induced
warming of the globe, carbon monoxide does not contribute to warming.
Unlike carbon dioxide however, it has the potential to significantly
influence atmospheric chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because carbon monoxide is a substance which has undergone only
a partial chemical reaction, and thus has great potential to react
further: for those of you who recall the OIL RIG acronym (Oxidation Is
Loss, Reduction Is Gain) from chemistry class relating to
oxygen/electron transfer, carbon monoxide is a reducing agent: i.e. it
removes oxygen from other molecules. Consequently, in combination with
other pollutants and the light from the Sun carbon monoxide is involved
in reactions which form dangerous tropospheric ozone and also urban smog
— both a nuisance and significant hazard to human health and the
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to its reactive nature, its lifetime in the atmosphere is quite
short (a few months only). As a result, the concentrations of carbon
monoxide are very unevenly distributed (i.e. it is heterogeneous).
Without time to persist and travel large distances, the highest carbon
monoxide concentrations in the atmosphere are found close to emission
sources. This makes it particularly useful for highlighting centres of
human activity and also changes in activity over relatively short
time-scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon monoxide emissions have been measured in the troposphere
continuously by satellite since March 2000 by an instrument named MOPITT
(Measurements of Pollution In The Troposphere). It is an instrument
designed and built by the Canadian Space Agency (CSA), and housed
on-board NASA’s polar-orbiting Terra satellite. Horizontally, these
measurements cover the whole globe. Vertically they are most sensitive
to CO in the middle troposphere (~500mb or 12,000 feet). MOPITT
requires cloud-free (clear-sky) atmosphere to determine carbon monoxide,
consequently this causes some issues with high-latitude data (&amp;gt;65
degrees), as problematic identification of cloud cover over
high-latitude ice-covered surfaces can cause some errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently performed a study on the MOPITT data, in this work—&lt;a href="http://www.mdpi.com/2225-1154/2/1/1"&gt;available
in the open access MDPI journal
Climate&lt;/a&gt;. I initially wanted to see
if the pollution measurements could be used to identify periodic
variations in emissions over regional scales at time-scales of several
days to several weeks. Identifying cycles in pollution over large areas
would have been useful to explore the sensitivity of cloud properties to
human emissions - an important area of study in atmospheric science. To
do this, my co-author Tariq Shahbaz, and I applied Lomb-Scargle period
analysis techniques, and Monte Carlo significance testing. We used
relatively large spatial scales (Europe, USA, and China) as identifying
small-scale periods would not have helped us to subsequently examine
cloud properties (which are very noisy data, and so it is preferential
to examine them over large areas to reduce variability). An example of
the period analysis shown in the paper is given below for the European
region (you can see the paper itself for further discussion). Although
we didn't identify any cycles useful for this in this data, a range of
evidence suggests that such cycles they do exist at a variety of
horizontal and vertical scales (which we provide a brief discussion of
in the paper) and work on this topic continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/Zoom_period.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lomb-Scargle periodogram over the European region for seasonally
de-trended CO data. A sub-plot shows a zoom on the only region of the
periodogram to show a statistically significant signal at the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt;
0.01 level -— the significance threshold is indicated by the red line
(calculated from Monte Carlo methods described in the paper). The
significant peak corresponds to a frequency of 2.286 days, and was found
to be an artefact, present at all domains, related to the orbital period
of the Terra satellite. Adapted from Figure 4–5 of Laken &amp;amp; Shahbaz,
2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, we were motivated to use the opportunity to examine how
carbon monoxide in the troposphere has changed over the past decade.
Globally, the data shows an overall decline in the amount of
tropospheric carbon monoxide of nearly 7% over the 2000–2012 period.
This could be related to increasing efficiency of combustion technology,
and researchers have long noted that tropospheric CO shows a declining
trend driven by increasingly more efficient combustion technology
(e.g.&lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/263/5153/1587.short"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;).
For clarity, I note that it is perfectly possible for the greenhouse gas
carbon dioxide to be increasing over the past decade (&lt;a href="http://keelingcurve.ucsd.edu"&gt;as they have been
doing&lt;/a&gt;) whilst carbon monoxide
concentrations can simultaneously decrease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/Fig_global.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Globally averaged measurements of CO from MOPITT (Ver 5, Lev 3 combined
product) with 360-day running mean (red line). Significant linear trend
of &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;=-2.97×10^13^&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;+1.89×10^18^, &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;=-0.42, &lt;em&gt;df&lt;/em&gt;=44, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; 0.01.
Equivalent to a net CO reduction of 6.58% (or 0.56% per year). Adapted
from Figure 1 of Laken &amp;amp; Shahbaz, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I note that I can’t say for certain that the decreasing trend is
completely physical, as long-term changes in satellite-detected
observations have also been known to be attributed to decay in the
instruments over time, as space is a harsh environment in which to
operate and instruments on-board satellites tend to decay, whilst at the
same time the orbiting satellites themselves loose altitude as a result
of drag on the Earth’s tenuous atmosphere leading to an inevitable
return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that when you look at carbon monoxide changes over smaller
scales during the past decade the picture becomes more interesting than
a simple decrease. There are large differences between regions — these
reflect the changes in global society over the past decade - in
particular we see that although on average carbon monoxide decreased
over the globe, pollution over China, India and across the Asian region
has undergone statistically significant increases: these are almost
certainly linked with increasing industrial activity and economic growth
over the regions. Similar increases in different types of pollution have
also been previously reported (e.g. &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v437/n7055/abs/nature04092.html"&gt;increasing nitrous oxide emissions
over
China&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also observed an increase in carbon monoxide pollution over areas of
Africa and South America (although these changes covered a smaller area
and were less intense than those seen over the Asian region). Biomass
burning was previously a primary factor in driving emissions over these
regions, however, it is likely that the increasing trend over the past
decade is attributed to industrial development. Indeed, these changes
could represent a rise of major Southern Hemisphere contributors to
atmospheric pollution, with significant implications for air quality and
health over the regions, such as suggested by &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/302/5651/1716.short"&gt;Akimoto
(2003)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="images/Spatial_fig.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linear trends in CO between March 2000 and April 2012 for (a) all
pixels, and (b) statistically significant (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; 0.05 two-tailed
level) pixels only. For each pixel, the values are obtained by
subtracting the last point of a linear regression over the full
time-period from the first point (i.e. the values are a linear change
over a 1D time series of each pixel individually). For each pixel,
statistical significance was calculated independently by comparison of
observed values to a probability density function obtained by Monte
Carlo procedures. Adapted from Figure 3 of Laken &amp;amp; Shahbaz, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="Pollution"></category><category term="Statistics"></category><category term="Remote sensing"></category></entry></feed>